<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Mobile Development | Jamie's Space]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamiepenney.github.io/categories/mobile-development/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamiepenney.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-05-16T09:43:05+12:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamiepenney.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jamie Penney]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fun with the Symbian Emulator]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamiepenney.github.io/2009/08/09/fun-with-the-symbian-emulator/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-09T00:52:16+12:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamiepenney.github.io/2009/08/09/fun-with-the-symbian-emulator</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The other night I stumbled on the PyS60 project, an open source port of the python runtime to Symbian S60 based phones. I own a Nokia N95, and I got kind of excited about this because I would like to mess around with development for it but can't bring myself to work with C++ in my spare time.</p>

<p>I thought it would be pretty easy to develop for as Python is interpreted, I thought I could just edit text files on the phone and run them to test them out. Turns out you can't do that (not easily anyway), you need to package them on your computer, then upload the package to the phone, then install it, then run it. That killed that idea.</p>

<p>I looked at the Symbian emulator, and the PyS60 team have a mod for it that installs the python runtime so you can just run script files on the emulated phone. "This is great!" I think, before actually trying it.</p>

<p>For starters, the python runtime doesn't work in the emulator when the emulator is running on Windows 7 x64 - damn. I have a VPC image with Windows XP on it though, so I fire that up, install everything, then try run it. The emulator crashes after about 15 seconds of loading.</p>

<p>After browsing the Nokia forums for a while, I find out the problem. VPC is actually connecting to the virtual machine over RDP, and so the audio drivers are the RDP Remote Audio drivers.</p>

<p>What do audio drivers have to do with a phone emulator I hear you ask? Good question, but it is one the Nokia forum dwellers have no answer for. Many people have complained that the Symbian Emulator does not work when connecting to the machine hosting it via RDP. There are other issues with particular sound card drivers or applications also causing it to crash. This is a prime example of bad error handling. Why, if the audio part of the emulator cannot work with some drivers, does it crash instead of continuing without audio?</p>

<p>So that brought down my plans for making<a href="http://www.wired.com/gadgetlab/2008/12/iphone-fart-app/"> millions of dollars from fart applications</a> for Symbian based phones.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
